var array = [{date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "During this event, William the Pig and Hugh the Iron offered free transport, but took their unwitting passengers to Tunisia. A leader of this event is apocryphally said to have performed miracles at the CathedralSaint-Denis.Oneleaderofthiscampaign,StephenofCloyes[kloy],saidhehad a letter from Jesus to the King of France. Nicholas of Cologne’s prediction that the sea by Genoa would part for this campaign obviously did not come true, and when this crusade ended, most of its participants were sold into slavery. For the point, name this 1212 crusade named for its youthful participants.", ANSWER: "Children's Crusade"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "The first female holder of this position wrote about her experiences in her book Why Women Should Rule The World. Dee Dee Myers held this post under Bill Clinton. This position was revamped under FDR by the grandson of a Confederate general, Stephen Early. A 1993 bill requiring background checks for firearm purchases is named after a holder of this position who was severely injured during the assassination attempt on Ronald Reagan. James Brady held, for the point, what position that manages briefings to White House media?", ANSWER: "Press Secretary"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "During this event, thousands of prisoners were held at the ESMA, a former school for naval mechanics. The Mothers of the Plaza de Mayo hold annual protests over people who disappeared in this event, many of whom were dropped into the Atlantic Ocean during Death Flights. This event began after the kidnapping of students in the Night of the Pencils, marking the start of the National Reorganization Process. Jorge Videla’s government instigated, for the point, what period of violence against perceived leftist insurgents in Argentina?", ANSWER: "Dirty War"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This work’s argument may have been inspired by a meeting with Carl Melchior. This work ominously ended by warning that men listen to whatever “hope, illusion, or revenge” is given to them during “economic privation.” This book, whose ideas were roughly implemented much later by the Marshall Plan, attacked a so-called “Carthaginian peace” and foresaw the devastating inflation that reparations would create. For the point, name this 1919 work that criticized the strict conditions imposed on Germany by the Treaty of Versailles, written by John Maynard Keynes.", ANSWER: "Economic Consequences of the Peace"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "On the morning of this battle, a group known as the “Red Devils” charged across a valley in the face of musket fire. The loser of this battle was left only with a smaller force on Mount Nangu after a catastrophic miscalculation caused the exposed right flank of the Western Army to be destroyed. The siege of Ueda Castle delayed Hidetada, the son of the winner of this battle, from reaching it in time. Ishida Mitsunari was killed at this battle, which helped end of the Toyotomi clan’s dominance. For the point, name this 1600 battle won by Tokugawa Ieyasu.", ANSWER: "Sekigahara"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "In this country’s most recent presidential election, Tatsiana Karatkevich finished second with 4 percent of the vote, though “against all candidates” received 6 percent. In 2002, it was revealed that the pension given to this country’s former leader, Stanislav Shushkevich, amounted to less than $2 a month. Journalist Iryna Khalip has been imprisoned for her criticism of this country’s president, who was opposed by the Zubr movement in the 2006 Jeans Revolution. For the point, name this former Soviet republic that has been led since 1994 by Alexander Lukashenko from Minsk.", ANSWER: "Belarus"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This was the first crime for which the outlaw John Murrell was imprisoned. Doc Middleton was one of the most notorious committers of this crime, which inspired the creation of a society in Dedham, Massachusetts aimed at cracking down on it. This was the only crime for which Belle Starr was ever arrested. Migrants heading westward were often victims of this crime at the hands of Great Plains Indians who were looking to improve the speed at which they could track buffalo. For the point, name this crime, the speciality of a gang called the “Pony Boys.”", ANSWER: "Horse theft"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Albertus Magnus claimed that cannons were used at a 1246-1247 siege of this European city; if true, that would make that siege the first known engagement in the western world to use gunpowder. The Etymologiae was an encyclopedic work compiled by a saint from this city named Isidore. This city’s namesake cathedral contains a prominent bell-tower known as the Giralda and is the largest cathedral in the world. Mud ́ejar architectural motifs were used in the creation of the Alcazar of this city found close to the port of Cadiz. For the point, name this major Spanish city of Andalusia.", ANSWER: "Seville"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "According to legend, this man’s advisor realized he made a mistake in tactics after hearing a woman scolding her son for eating hot gruel. The satraps Nicanor and Philip may have been killed by this man’s forces. A thousand mile road built during this man’s rule from Pataliputra to Bihar was recorded in history by Megasthenes. This man, who was succeeded by Bindusara, overthrew the Nanda Dynasty. For the point, name this grandfather of Ashoka and founder of the Mauryan Dynasty.", ANSWER: "Chandragupta"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "An “official peace version” of this song from 1919 rewrites its warlike second stanza. Muzio Clementi paid tribute to his adopted land by quoting this song in his Great National Symphony, and early versions of this song included a verse celebrating Field Marshal Wade in opposition to the Jacobites. John Bull is sometimes cited as the composer of this song’s melody, which is also used for the national anthem of Liechtenstein and the American song “My Country, Tis of Thee.” For the point, name this national anthem of the United Kingdom.", ANSWER: "God Save the Queen"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Philip of Dreux captured William Longsword at this battle where Renald of Boulange was the last to surrender. The shield of the Montmorency family has 16 eagles instead of 4 because Mathieu de Montmorency captured 12 banners at this battle. Ferrand of Flanders broke an alliance before this battle, which led to the overthrow of Holy Roman Emperor Otto IV by Frederick II. Shortly after this battle, the losing king was forced to sign the Magna Carta. For the point, name this 1214 battle where Philip II of France defeated John I of England.", ANSWER: "Bouvines"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "The Supreme Court ruled it unconstitutional to censor these things because they were deemed sacrilegious in Joseph Burstyn v. Wilson. In 1948, the “Big Five” was stopped from block booking these things. Marvin Miller’s advertising of books and these things led the Supreme Court to create a new three-prong standard for defining obscenity. The Citizens United case was initially inspired by one of these works about Hillary Clinton. The Hays Code restricted the moral character of, for the point, what form of entertainment produced by Warner Brothers and MGM?", ANSWER: "Film"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This group’s predecessors included the ROPCIO and KOR, and its actions led to the amending of its nation’s constitution in the April Novelization. This group chose strategically significant dates, such as the signing of the July Manifesto and its country’s 1791 constitution, for its protests and strikes. This organization engaged the government of Wojciech Jaruzelski in the Round Table Talks, securing free elections in 1989. For the point, name this group that was founded at the Lenin Shipyards in Gdansk, a Polish trade union once led by Lech Walesa.", ANSWER: "Solidarity"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This city, which was settled by colonists from the ship Anne, was laid out according to a plan that arranged four residential blocks and four commercial blocks around an open square. The British commander Augustin Prevost defended this city during a Revolutionary War siege that claimed the life of Casimir Pulaski. James Oglethorpe founded this city as the capital of his new colony. William Tecumseh Sherman’s March to the Sea ended with the capture of, for the point, what Georgia port city?", ANSWER: "Savannah"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Elizabeth Harris was one of the first preachers of this religious group in America. Diary-writer John Woolman convinced many members of this religious group to free their slaves. Mary Dyer was one of three people from this group executed in Massachusetts called the Boston Martyrs. A leader of this group signed a treaty with the Lenape under a white oak tree, established a colony dubbed the “Holy Experiment,” and founded the city of Philadelphia. For the point, name this religious group once led by William Penn that is also known as the Society of Friends.", ANSWER: "Quakers"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This leader had his Chief Justice, Benedicto Kiwanuka, murdered shortly after taking power. As a general, this man forced his country’s Kabaka people into exile at the Battle of Mengo Hill. This leader took power in a coup while his predecessor was attending a Commonwealth Conference in Singapore. This leader was ousted after he launched a failed invasion of the Kagera region of his southern neighbor, and he infamously gave his country’s Asian population 90 days to leave the country. For the point, name this Ugandan dictator for most of the 1970s.", ANSWER: "Idi Amin"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "A governor of this state was criticized for her role in the botched execution of Clayton Lockett. In 2015, a senator from this state threw a snowball on the floor of the Senate to mock the concept of climate change. Mary Fallin and Jim Inhofe are politicians from this state, whose former Attorney General proposed a public televised debate between researchers on climate science as part of his work as Administrator of the EPA. For the point, name this home state of Scott Pruitt.", ANSWER: "Oklahoma"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Swanson’s Law states that the price of these items falls 20 percent for every doubling of industry capacity. The Shockley-Queisser limit gives the theoretical maximum efficiency of these devices, which operate when absorption results in electron-hole pairs. In 2017, a hoax claimed that lobbyists made it illegal to use these devices in the aftermath of Hurricane Irma; in reality, safety laws require their disconnection from the grid to protect repair crews and linemen. A start-up company that built these devices, Solyndra, went bankrupt in 2011. For the point, name these photovoltaic devices that convert sunlight into electricity.", ANSWER: "Solar cell"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "In an address to the Senate, this man claimed that the gravest question, “How can the Union be preserved?”, could only be answered by the North, not the South. This man claimed that every civilization was founded upon a system of two classes in a speech that labeled slavery as “a positive good.” James Murray Mason delivered this man’s speech in opposition to the Compromise of 1850 on March 4 in the month of his death. For the point, name this South Carolina senator and states’ rights advocate, a member of the Great Triumvirate.", ANSWER: "Calhoun"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Clive Caldwell praised an “undervalued” aircraft produced by this country, a plane nicknamed Folgore that was developed from the C200 Saetta. This country formed the CAI to fight in the Battle of Britain, and one of its ships later became the Yugoslavian presidential yacht Galeb. After this country’s naval signals were intercepted by the Allies, it lost the Battle of Cape Matapan in 1941, and one of its Littorio-class battleships was sunk by German Fritz-Xs after it signed an armistice with the Allies in 1943. For the point, name this country whose Regia Marina was led by Admiral Angelo Iachino.", ANSWER: "Italy"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This mountain was first scaled by botanist Edwin James. Nikola Tesla built his first functional coil while working on this mountain. The namesake of this mountain was killed while commanding troops at the Battle of York and had previously led a Westward expedition until his capture in Santa Fe. The “Fifty-Niners” were a group of gold miners whose slogan was “[this mountain] or bust.” Katharine Bates wrote the song “America the Beautiful” after being inspired by the view from the summit of, for the point, what peak of the Colorado Rockies, named in honor of a 19th-century explorer named Zebulon?", ANSWER: "Pikes"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Policeman Greg Kading alleged that this man was killed by a man nicknamed “Poochie.” Shaquille O’Neal has claimed that his presence at an after-party might have prevented this man’s death. The Police’s “Every Breath You Take” was sampled in “I’ll Be Missing You,” a song written in memory of this man. A man in a blue suit and bowtie opened fire on this man’s Chevrolet Suburban in 1997, just six months after his rival was similarly shot and killed in Las Vegas. For the point, name this rapper behind the album Ready to Die, an East Coast rival of Tupac Shakur.", ANSWER: "Notorious B.I.G"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "In this country, after the local population resisted the Soviet takeover, Dashnak and Bolshevik forces massacred thousands of people during the March Days. The Musavat Party turned this country into the first Muslim secular democracy before it was overthrown during the Russian Civil War. Soldiers from this country murdered thousands of people of a neighboring ethnicity in the 1920 Shusha Massacre over the status of Nagorno-Karabakh. For the point, name this Caucasian country that fought for three years, and continues to feud, with Armenia.", ANSWER: "Azerbaijan"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "A group rioted in this city with the slogan “bring the war home” during the 1969 Days of Rage. That direct action protest by the Weathermen was denounced by Fred Hampton, the leader of this city’s Black Panther Party, who was killed by the FBI and members of this city’s police department in a raid later that year. Abraham Ribicoff denounced the “Gestapo-like” tactics used to suppress protests during the 1968 Democratic National Convention by mayor Richard Daley in, for the point, what largest city in Illinois?", ANSWER: "Chicago"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This man agreed to limit his own power in the Second Settlement shortly after he was accused of meddling in a trial involving Marcus Primus. The religious altar Ara Pacis was commissioned by this man to serve as a monument to the period of peace he ruled over, the Pax Romana. This man came to power after his admiral Marcus Agrippa was victorious at the Battle of Actium, ending a struggle with Marc Antony. For the point, name this adopted son of Caesar who was crowned Rome’s first emperor.", ANSWER: "Augustus"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "A literary magazine in this country, Angry Penguins, fell for a hoax involving the fictitious poet Ern Malley; that hoax inspired the 2003 novel My Life as a Fake. Laura Trevelyan is a character in a novel based on the German explorer Ludwig Leichhardt’s death in this country’s desert. For the point, name this country, the setting of many Peter Carey novels and Patrick White’s Voss, which discusses a German explorer who died in its sparse Outback region.", ANSWER: "Australia"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "The Presidential Unit Citation and two of these decorations were given to Sergeant Reckless, a horse. A civilian award analogous to this medal is the Secretary of Defense Medal for the Defense of Freedom. The Badge of Military Merit was the predecessor of this award, whose medal depicts a gold-colored George Washington in profile. While serving as the officer of a Swift Boat during the Vietnam War, John Kerry received three of, for the point, what military decoration given to soldiers who are wounded or killed in service?", ANSWER: "Purple Heart"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This woman’s uncle, the Duke of Cumberland, dissolved the Constitution of Hanover, leading to criticism from the Brothers Grimm. King Leopold I served as the matchmaker for this woman, his niece. Edward Oxford was ruled mentally insane after trying to kill this person. Robert Peel chose not to be Prime Minister because this leader failed to dismiss her Ladies of the Bedchamber. This woman married a man who planned the 1851 Crystal Palace Exhibition. For the point, name this Queen of England who married Prince Consort Albert and ruled for over six decades.", ANSWER: "Victoria"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Rogier Verbeek studied one of these events, having directly witnessed it from Buitenzorg. One of these events is hypothesized to have occurred in late 1808, based on a peak in sulfate concentration in Arctic ice cores and South American descriptions of atmospheric anomalies. One of these events at Mount Tambora caused 1816 to be a “year without a summer.” The red sky in Edward Munch’s The Scream was inspired by one of these events that devastated islands in the Sunda Strait. For the point, name this type of event that, in 1883, destroyed the island of Krakatoa and killed tens of thousands of people with pyroclastic flows.", ANSWER: "Eruption"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "A sitting Chief Justice once compared the relationship between the government and this Native American people to that of a “ward to its guardian.” Elizur Butler was a missionary who was arrested for living on this people’s lands, breaking a state law. Andrew Jackson refused to abide by a Marshall Court ruling regarding these people that established the doctrine of Native American sovereignty. Worcester v. Georgia concerned the lands of, for the point, what people who were relocated to Oklahoma in the final portion of the Trail of Tears?", ANSWER: "Cherokee"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Bill 80” provided for raising troops during this war. Troops called up by the NRMA in this war who refused active duty service were derisively nicknamed “zombies.” Maurice Duplessis lost a provincial election on a platform of opposing this war, which caused the second of two major conscription crises in Candian history. Mackenzie King’s third term as prime minister included the duration of this war. For the point, name this war during which Canadian troops captured Juno Beach on D-Day.", ANSWER: "WWII", ANSWER2: "World War II", ANSWER3: "World War 2"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "A physician who worked for this woman wrote Discourse on the Existence of Ghosts, which explained that lack of oxygen could cause failure for corpses to decompose. This woman’s husband lost the Duchy of Lorraine but was given the Grand Duchy of Tuscany instead. Marshal Neipperg lost the Battle of Mollwitz in a war that broke out after this woman gained the throne. In the Treaty of Breslau, this leader ceded much of Silesia to Frederick the Great. For the point, name this queen whose rise to power in 1740 triggered the War of the Austrian Succession.", ANSWER: "Theresa"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "Robert Church Jr. founded a league named after this man that paid poll taxes to promote African-American voter turnout in the South. Moe Fishman was a member and representative of a group named after this person that sustained heavy casualties at the Battles of Jarama and Brunete. The village of Lancaster was renamed after this person as part of an effort to move a state capital south of the Platte River. A brigade of international volunteers in the Spanish Civil War was named after, for the point, what namesake of Nebraska’s capital city?", ANSWER: "Lincoln"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This figure issued the “23 Articles” as a follow-up to his “Former Ten Points,” which opposed the emphasis on corruption in two other reports. “Bombard the Headquarters” was the name of a big-character poster written by this figure during a campaign in which his successor died in a plane crash while fleeing to the Soviet Union. Lin Biao was condemned as a traitor by this man’s government. For the point, name this instigator of the Cultural Revolution and first Communist leader of China.", ANSWER: "Mao"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This city’s Academy of Saint Luke hosted lectures by artists who worked in this city like Federico Zuccaro. A scholarship established by Louis XIV called the “Prix [pree] de” [this place] allowed French architects and painters to study in this city. A statue of a personification of this city sits on a pedestal containing reliefs of a wolf and two infants in Jacques-Louis David’s depiction of lictors bringing bodies to Lucius Junius Brutus. The Trevi Fountain is located in, for the point, what Italian city?", ANSWER: "Rome", ANSWER2: "Roma"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.1", question: "This politician proclaimed “I will be your Moses!” while campaigning in his home state. This politician, who attempted to stall the Fenian Raids into Canada, defeated William Brownlow for Congress in 1845 as a defender of the poor. This man’s dislike of Southern planter aristocracy led him to stay loyal to the Union; after the South seceded, this Tennesseean became the only Southern Senator to not resign. For the point, name this National Union Vice President who became President after the assassination of Abraham Lincoln.", ANSWER: "Johnson",},
             //2018.NatsBee.2
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This leader offered to take in 100,000 Jewish refugees at the Evian Conference, although only 800 Jews were settled in the town of Sosua. This leader was killed in an ambush of his blue Chevrolet while travelling towards San Cristobal. The International Day for the Elimination of Violence against Women is on the anniversary of the assassination of the Mirabal sisters, who opposed this leader. Johnny Abbes Garcia led this leader’s secret police force, known as the SIM. This leader ordered killings of thousands of Haitians in the Parsley Massacre. For the point, name this longtime dictator of the Dominican Republic.", ANSWER: "Trujilo"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "During this event, the 28th Mountain Division attempted to break out to the city of Tuzla but were ambushed at Kamenica Hill. The Dutchbat were forced to retreat by the VRS prior to this event. The Drina Valley surrounding this event’s location was mistakenly declared a “safe area.” Forces under Ratko Mladi ́c       were responsible for this event, which Kofi Annan labeled as the worst mass murder in Europe since World War II. For the point, name this 1995 massacre of Muslim Bosniaks in a namesake town.", ANSWER: "Srebenica"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "A film executive who would go on to become a mayor in Florida was listed at the beginning of this document. Charles Colson authored this document, which he compiled while serving as a “hatchet man.” Daniel Schorr read this document on public television, expressing surprise at finding his own name on it. John Dean revealed the existence of this document, whose subjects were to be targeted with IRS tax audits and restrictions on government contracts. A set of hearings in 1973 brought to light, for the point, what infamous list that included actor Paul Newman and 19 other political opponents of a US president?", ANSWER: "Nixon's enemy list"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "While fighting at the First Battle of Ypres [eep], this man took a sniper’s bullet through the lung, taking him out of World War I for 3 years. After World War II, this man served as the first Deputy Supreme Allied Commander of Europe. This man critically chose to have eight, rather than three, divisions make up the landing force on D-Day. This man was described as a “tired little fart” by George Patton, who this man helped to take Sicily. This leader of the Eighth Army won the Second Battle of El Alamein during the North African Campaign. For the point, name this British general.", ANSWER: "Montgomery"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "In this modern-day country, a man claimed to have received a vision from a “Maid of Heaven” while imprisonedintheSiyah-Chal.AsChancellor,AmirKabirwasnotoriousforsuppressing minority religions in this country, where Subh-i-Azal led a splinter religious faction claiming to be the true followers of the Ba ́b [bob], who initially claimed to be Mahdi. Followers of a religion founded in this country built the Universal House of Justice in Haifa, Israel. For the point, name this country where the Baha’i Faith was founded and has been persecuted by Ayatollah Khamenei.", ANSWER: "Iran"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "A member of the Little Circle named John Edward Taylor founded this newspaper in 1821. This paper claimed that “neither side can escape condemnation” for a 1972 incident at Bogside. This newspaper published a scoop on a scandal in which a murdered 11-year old named Milly Dowler and victims of a 2005 metro bombing had their phones hacked by News of the World, which led to Rupert Murdoch’s resignation. Edward Snowden initially leaked his information to, for the point, what left-leaning British daily newspaper?", ANSWER: "Guardian"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This man’s army was defeated at the Battle of Yongqiu, delaying his attempts to capture the city of Suiyang. This man was granted a post as commander of the Pinglu garrison thanks to his friendship with Yang Guifei. This man benefited from the incompetence of Yang Guozhong, who was strangled by his own soldiers as the emperor Xuanzong fled Chang’an before this man. This man proclaimed the Yan Dynasty in an uprising that may have killed five percent of the world’s population. For the point, name this Sogdian general who rebelled against the Tang Dynasty in the 8th century.", ANSWER: "An Lushan"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "In a 1985 operation titled for one of these objects, Israeli F-15s struck a Tunisian PLO base in retaliation for a series of killings carried out by Force 17. One of these objects was used to kill commander ArthurAstoninthesiegeofDrogheda.Ageneralknownas“OldSilverNails”begantouse one of these objects after a failed raid on Saint Martin. One of these objects is on display in Springfield, Illinois, having been captured by the 4th Illinois Infantry during the Mexican-American War; that object was originally used after its owner was struck by a cannonball during the Pastry War. The governor of New Amsterdam, Peter Stuyvesant, used, for the point, what type of prosthesis used by Santa Anna?", ANSWER: "Leg"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "While this man was fighting a war against the Parthians, he was forced to face a Jewish rebellion known as the Kitos War. This man won the Second Battle of Tapae against Decebalus and names a bridge across the Danube that assisted in his invasion. Pliny the Younger asked this man how to deal with Christians in Bithynia. He celebrated his 106 AD conquest of Dacia by building a column in his imperial forum. For the point, name this Roman Emperor who expanded the Roman Empire to its greatest extent.", ANSWER: "Trajan"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This composer wrote the score to a documentary about war refugees relocating to Cummington, Massachusetts, as well as the score to a film featuring Greenbelt, Maryland, The City, that premiered at the 1939 World’s Fair. This man wrote a piece for the Ballet Caravan that quotes “Goodbye Old Paint” and “Git Along, Little Dogies” and features the title outlaw in a percussion-heavy “Gun Battle” being he is killed by Pat Garrett. For the point, name this American composer of Billy The Kid who included a “Hoe-Down” at the end of his ballet Rodeo.", ANSWER: "Copland"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "The presidential election of this year was satirized by the political cartoon “A Foot Race” and marked the end of the King Caucus system. In this election year, Nathaniel Macon replaced Albert Gallatin as the vice presidential candidate on a ticket led by the sitting Secretary of the Treasury. William Crawford ran for the presidency in this election year, in which Henry Clay received a “corrupt bargain” by trading support in the House of Representatives for the position of Secretary of State. For the point, name this election year in which John Quincy Adams won the presidency.", ANSWER: "1824"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This leader once received a gift of 31 live myrrh trees after establishing trading relations with the Land of Punt. As a sign of recovery from the Hyksos occupation, this leader embarked on building projects like the Red Chapel at Karnak and the Unfinished Obelisk in Aswan. This pharaoh was interred in the first Valley of the Kings tomb built, KV20, although many monuments dedicated to this pharaoh were later effaced by Thutmose III, her son and co-regent. For the point, name this prominent female Egyptian pharaoh of the 18th Dynasty.", ANSWER: "Hatshepsut"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "A rebel exiled from this country led the hijacking of the cruise ship Santa Maria in 1961. The Flechas were a unit of natives that helped this country police its colonies. A fugitive member of the OAS founded Aginter Press in this country while serving as a cover for an anti-communist mercenary force. Immigrants who arrived in this country after the end of its colonial empire were known as the retornados. Antonio Salazar established the Estado Novo regime in, for the point, what country where the Carnation Revolution took place in Lisbon?", ANSWER: "Portugal"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "Immigrants from the Panyu district carried this language to the United States. Yuan Chonghuan’s battle cry was used in protests over this language in 2010. This is the prestige dialect of the Yue language group, which also includes such languages as Toishanese. According to legend, this language almost became the national language after the 1911 Xinhai Revolution. The primary language in Guangdong Province is, for the point, what southern Chinese dialect, spoken in Guangzhou and Hong Kong, that is mutually unintelligible to Mandarin?", ANSWER: "Cantonese"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This speech quotes Speaker John Carlisle on the “struggle between the idle holders of idle capital and the struggling masses who produce the wealth.” This speech, which compares Cicero’s exposure of the Cataline plot to Andrew Jackson’s anti-bank policy, ended with its speaker holding his arms outstretched. This speech urged the masses not to “press down upon the brow of labor this crown of thorns” in a condemnation of the gold standard. For the point, name this speech given at the 1896 Democratic National Convention by William Jennings Bryan.", ANSWER: "Cross of Gold"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "The Willis-Graham Act allowed this company to become a monopoly by repealing the Kingsburg Commitment. Theodore Vail led this company towards “One Policy, One System, Universal Service.” Western Electric provided equipment to this company, which controversially would not allow Hush-A- Phone corporation to add attachments to its telephones. In the resulting anti-trust case, this company was divided into “Baby Bells.” For the point, name this company that was founded in 1885 by Alexander Graham Bell and was once the world’s largest telephone company.", ANSWER: "AT&T"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This country’s ports were blockaded by its southern neighbor after it lost the Battle of Punta Malpelo. Jose Antonio Paez led the La Cosiata movement to break away from this country. The Congress of Cucuta created this country and named Francisco de Paula Santander as its vice president. This country existed for twelve years until the secession of Venezuela and Ecuador, ending Simon Bolivar’s dream of a united South American state. For the point, name this former South American country whose name lives on in a successor state south of Panama.", ANSWER: "Gran Colombia"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "Granville Sharp, a member of the Clapham Sect, supported this movement by founding the St. Georges Bay Company. In an interpretation of common law, Lord Mansfield supported this cause in the Somerset case. This cause drew strength after sailors on the Zong threw men overboard and tried to collect insurance on the dead. The medallion Am I Not a Man and a Brother? and the autobiography of freedman Olaudah Equiano were created to support, for the point, what movement led by William Wilberforce in England that inspired the creation of Sierra Leone’s city of Freetown?", ANSWER: "Abolition"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This author’s Plutarch-inspired Representative Men characterizes Napoleon as the “Man of the World.” This author, who wrote a letter defending the Cherokee nation to Martin van Buren, hypothesized an entity that connects the essences of all human beings in his Eastern-inspired essay, “The Over-Soul.” This man championed individualism in speeches such as “The Poet” and “Self-Reliance.” For the point, name this American transcendentalist and author of the essay “Nature.”", ANSWER: "Emerson"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This location was the subject of an influential pamphlet by Sir Humphrey Gilbert, who lost his first fleet and died on a second attempt to reach this location. The Company of Cathay was founded after Martin Frobisher’s failed attempt to find this location ended in a possible discovery of gold. Sir John Franklin’s lost expedition was meant to traverse this location, a task finally completed by Roald Amundsen in 1905. Melting Arctic ice now allows relatively easy shipping through, for the point, what long-sought sea route through North America?", ANSWER: "Northwest Passage"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This country employed Adam Laxman to return two Japanese castaways in exchange for trade concessions. Cecil Spring Rice orchestrated an Anglo-Japanese alliance, as he believed it was the only way to contain this country. Under the Treaty of Shimoda, this country divided the Kuril islands with Japan. One of China’s unequal treaties, the 1860 Convention of Beijing, officially granted this country the Amur Annexation, a strip of land where it built the city of Vladivostok. For the point, name this country that negotiated total control of Sakhalin in the 1875 Treaty of St. Petersburg.", ANSWER: "Russia"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "The 2013 film The Missing Picture depicts the rule of this group in the form of clay animation. In 1997, Nate Thayer was able to conduct an interview with this group’s leader a year before he died. This group was responsible for killing around 40 percent of the Cham population, and it operated a prison that is now the Tuol Sleng Genocide Museum. This group was ousted from power after a 1979 invasion from neighboring Vietnam. For the point, name this communist group that was responsible for the killing fields in Cambodia under Pol Pot.", ANSWER: "Khmer Rouge"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "In this state’s capital, William West led a march with members of the Country Party in an effort to lobby for the Bill of Rights. The first major action of the Comte d’Estaing’s fleet in the Revolutionary War was at an abortive siege in this state. This was the home state of colonial commander Nathaniel Greene. John Brown and Abraham Whipple led the burning of a British customs enforcement schooner in this state in the Gaspee Affair. For the point, name this state where British forces held off a siege of Newport.", ANSWER: "Rhode Island"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "The “Traitorous Eight” left a lab dedicated to this technology to start a company of their own with the help of Sherman Fairchild; the lab they left was run by William Shockley, who shared the 1956 Nobel Prize in Physics with Walter Brattain and John Bardeen for discovering these devices. These devices are often made using germanium or silicon, which gives Silicon Valley its name due to their crucial presence in computers. For the point, name this type of material that has conductivity between that of insulators and conductors.", ANSWER: "semiconductors"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "A character in this work repeatedly paints a pond in his backyard to get over the death of his daughter, Marigold. The main character of this work learns of her father’s death while on a Kenyan safari. In this work, Vanessa Kirby portrays a woman who falls in love with a divorced air force group leader, Peter Townshend. The first episode of this series focuses on a lavish wedding in which Philip, Duke of Edinburgh marries into the royal family. For the point, name this Netflix series about the life of Queen Elizabeth II.", ANSWER: "The Crown"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "Edgar Nixon hired this woman as his secretary despite his belief that “women don’t need to be nowhere but in the kitchen.” While working for the NAACP, this woman was sent to investigate the rape of Recy Taylor. This woman was preferred over Claudette Colvin for an event in which James Blake, a man who had once left her standing in the rain, ordered her arrest. For the point, name this woman who, on December 1, 1955, sparked the Montgomery Bus Boycott by refusing to move to the back of a bus.", ANSWER: "Parks"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "A variety of the M4 used by this country’s military was known as the Super Sherman. The SAR and MAR are two variants of a weapon developed in this country known as the Galil. A German-born colonel in this country’s military developed a submachine gun with a telescoping sight that was named after him. In the 1950s, this country’s military adopted the Uzi as a weapon to be used by its namesake Defense Forces, which had been established in 1948. For the point, name this country that employed the Jericho missile during the Yom Kippur War.", ANSWER: "Israel"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "The first of a series of extralegal conventions was held in this city’s Raleigh Tavern. The first psychiatric hospital in America was built in this city, that was originally named Middle Plantation. An argument over ownership of gunpowder stores in this city forced Lord Dunmore to flee it. A 1693 royal charter led to the creation of America’s second-oldest university in this city. The College of William and Mary is located in, for the point, what city that succeeded Jamestown as the capital of the Virginia colony?", ANSWER: "Williamsburg"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "Nicetas Chroniates made note of this woman’s eptithet, “golden foot.” One of this woman’s husbands considered divorcing her for the “Rose of Unchastity.” The Rolls of Oleron were promoted by this ruler as maritime law. This woman’s husband lost the Battle of Mount Cadmus in the Second Crusade. Andreas Cappellanus described this woman, Ermengande of Narbonne, and Isabelle of Flanders as operating a Court of Love in Poitiers. John I and Richard I of England were children of, for the point, what queen who married Louis VII and Henry II of England?", ANSWER: "Eleanor of Aquitane"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "A protest by workers who produced this good was led by Abbas Tyabji. A  barrier called the Great Hedge was erected to prevent the smuggling of this good, which was produced extensively in Dharasana. The Second Round Table Conference arose after a protest revolving around this good that ended after negotiations with Lord Irwin. Vedaranyam was the site of a protest against the taxation of, for the point, what good whose British taxation was protested by a march to Dandi led by Mahatma Gandhi, who broke the law by reclaiming this good from seawater?", ANSWER: "salt"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "The perpetrator of this action defended himself in the open letter “To the Inhabitants of America.” After this plot was exposed, the perpetrator fled to New York City on board the Vulture, where he was joined by his wife, Peggy Shippen. Henry Clinton agreed to pay 20,000 pounds to the perpetrator of this plot, which was exposed when John Andre was captured in Tarrytown. The British would have gained control over the Hudson River in, for the point, what failed act of treason during the Revolutionary War?", ANSWER: "Arnold West Point"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "Members of this organization lived in a safe house in Big Spring Park in Pennsylvania, from where they planned an attack on the Hungry Horse and Flathead Dams in Montana. Markus Hess was employed in the 1980s as a hacker by this organization, which created a poisoned jewel box in an attempt to kill Josip Tito. The GRU was the military counterpart to this organization, which saw many of its agents compromised during the Red Scare. The NKVD was a predecessor of, for the point, what Soviet security agency?", ANSWER: "KGB"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "One of these objects brought to the White House by Andrew Jackson in memory of Rachel Donelson is currently in poor condition. Nathaniel Coffin Jr. destroyed one of these objects in Boston that was a gathering place for Stamp Act protests. Connecticut’s Royal Charter of 1662 was hidden from Edmund Andros inside one of these objects. A Parson Weems biography relates how a six year old boy destroyed one of these objects. For the point, name these plants, one of which a young George Washington supposedly chopped down.", ANSWER: "Tree"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "This king gave the duchies of Saxony and Bavaria to Henry the Lion, who was later tried for insubordination after refusing to help this man. A unit known as the Company of Death helped thwart this man’s Roncaglia decrees, where this man had attempted to expand his power into Italy before losing at Legnano to the Lombard League. This man’s body was preserved in a barrel of vinegar after this man had drowned in the Saleph River whilst leading his armies to the Third Crusade. For the point, name this red-bearded Holy Roman Emperor.", ANSWER: "Barbarossa"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "A seated depiction of this man uses a background of leaves with chrysanthemums, jasmine and blue lilies; Kehinde Wiley, the artist of that portrait of this man for the National Portrait Gallery, intended for those flowers to represent this man’s heritage. Graphic designer Shepard Fairey used shades of blue and red to show this leader with the word “HOPE” in blue letters during this leader’s 2008 campaign. For the point, name this 44th President of the United States.", ANSWER: "Obama"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.2", question: "A Francis Poulenc opera is based on the executions of 16 women who served this organization in Compi`egne. The assignat was backed by the lands of this organization, which were broken up and sold in large plots. Napoleon restored the standing of this organization with the Concordat of 1801. Members of this organization who refused to follow a certain law were termed “refractory;” those members rejected the Civil Constitution of the Clergy. For the point, name this religious organization whose lands were confiscated during the French Revolution.", ANSWER: "Catholic"},
             //2018.NatsBee.3
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This empire’s naval commanders included the native Dutchman Jan Janszoon. In the 18th century, this empire’s capital was briefly taken over by the sailor Patrona Halil. This empire’s other naval commanders included Dragut, who served as a galley slave after this empire lost a pivotal battle. This empire’s most famous admiral was Hayrettin Barbarossa, and this empire’s fleet was defeated at the Battle of Navarino during its failed attempt to hold some of its territory. For the point, name this Islamic empire from which Greece won its independence.", ANSWER: "Ottoman"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "After J.C. Dunbar’s identity was discovered, Frank Wilson helped find evidence against this man, who was prosecuted using a method devised by Mable Walker Williebrandt. James Belcastro planted bombs for this man during the Pineapple Primary. This man, who often noted, “All I do is satisfy a public demand,” was mentored by Johnny Torrio and fought the North Side Gang in a turf war that eventually ended with Bugs Moran’s men being gunned down on Valentine’s Day. For the point, name this Chicago mobster, known as “Scarface,” who was convicted for income tax evasion in 1931.", ANSWER: "Capone"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This scientist derided James Jeans for not accepting that a certain value was nonzero. This scientist’s son Erwin was hanged for participating in the July 20 Plot to kill Adolf Hitler. Although this man signed the “Manifesto of the 93 Intellectuals,” he later rescinded his agreement with sections of it following discussions with Hendrik Lorentz. This man’s namesake law of blackbody radiation solved the “ultraviolet catastrophe.” For the point, name this quantum physicist whose namesake constant is represented with a lowercase h.", ANSWER: "Planck"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This man rebuked a magistrate by saying, “you are not addressing a third-class pleader.” This man’s fame in law began with the Caucus Case and a successful defense of Bal Gangadhar Tilak from sedition charges. Reforms in the North West Frontier Province and Balochistan were part of this politician’s 1929 presentation of Fourteen Points. The Lahore Resolution, demanding a separate nation, was passed under this man’s leadership. Liaquat Ali Khan served as prime minister with, for the point, what leader of the Muslim League and founder of Pakistan?", ANSWER: "Jinnah"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "A naval commander of this surname died leading the Randolph in combat against the Yarmouth during the Revolutionary War. Francis, a man with this surname, created a list of eleven subversive communist groups in 1941 and served as Attorney General during World War II. An organization led by a man with this surname applied to renew its charter in 1832, leading to conflict with Andrew Jackson. For the point, give this surname of Nicholas, the president of the Second Bank of the United States.", ANSWER: "Biddle"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This man executed his once-ally Lu ̈ Bu after previously allying with him to defeat his rival Dong Zhuo. While attempting to expand southwards, this man suffered a devastating naval defeat due to his enemy’s usage of fire ships; that loss came at the hands of Sun Quan and Liu Bei at the Battle of Red Cliffs. This man originally rose to power as a Chancellor of the Eastern Han dynasty in its waning days. For the point, name this Chinese warlord who is prominently portrayed as a villain in Romance of the Three Kingdoms.", ANSWER: "Cao Cao"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "Lintel construction was used by this civilization to build a gate featuring a pillar that separates two lions. Archaeologists study this civilization at sites like the megaron of Tiryns. Limestone half-columns adorned the portal of a “tholos” tomb built during this civilization that may have belonged to Atreus. Michael Ventris discovered a script used to write this civilization’s language called Linear B. The Mask of Agamemnon was created during, for the point, what Bronze Age Greek civilization that succeeded the Minoans?", ANSWER: "Mycenae"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This composer quoted the 10th-century hymn “Lord have mercy on us” in an oratorio about the title Christian duchess. This composer of Saint Ludmila was commissioned by Jeanette Thurber to write a Te Deum to celebrate the 400th anniversary of America’s discovery. This man was taught African-American spirituals by Harry Burleigh and wrote a symphony whose second movement opens with a English horn solo and was inspired by Longfellow’s Song of Hiawatha. For the point, name this Czech composer who subtitled his Symphony no. 9 in D minor “From the New World.”", ANSWER: "Dvorak"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "In legend, this natural feature was created by a battle between the sky god Skell and the god of the underworld, Llao. John Wesley Hillman was the first non-Native man to see this feature, which was used in Klamath vision quests. The Phantom Ship and Wizard Island are found in this body of water, as is a tree stump named Old Man of the Lake that has been bobbing in its waters since at least 1896. For the point, name this caldera lake that formed several thousand years ago from the eruption of Mount Mazama in Oregon, the deepest lake in the US.", ANSWER: "Crater"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "One side in this conflict was colonized via the Condominium Agreement. Emin Pasha was rescued by Henry Morton Stanley during this conflict, in which Menelik II was proclaimed emperor after an invasion of Ethiopia ended in Yohannes IV’s death at Gallabat. The Hadendoa people, who fought under Osman Digna, were nicknamed the “Fuzzy Wuzzys” during this war. Shortly after the Fashoda Incident during this conflict, Lord Kitchener wiped out the losing side at Omdurman. For the point, name this war started by a Sudanese self-proclaimed Islamic redeemer.", ANSWER: "Mahdi"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "During this campaign, the phrase “Washing Machine Charlie” was used to indicate planes carrying out nighttime attacks. Alexander Patch was the U.S. Army commander in this campaign, during which four Allied cruisers were sunk during an engagement at Savo Island. Henderson Field was a key objective during this battle, which was codenamed Operation Watchtower. This six-month-long battle began in August 1942 after Marines landed on a namesake island and the nearby Tulagi. For the point, name this World War II campaign that took place in the Solomon Islands.", ANSWER: "Guadalcanal"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "During this decade, Josef Bachmann shot a prominent figure who coined the phrase “long march through the institutions” as a strategy, Rudi Dutschke. The death of Benno Ohnesorg during this decade sparked a backlash against Kurt Kiesinger, who served as chancellor during the later half of this decade. The SDS, or Socialist German Student Union, arose as a movement during this decade, in which Willy Brandt began his term as chancellor. For the point, name this decade in which a resurgence of Marxism and student activism in West Germany mirrored the rise of the counterculture in the US.", ANSWER: "60s"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "During this event, Henry Wilson cleared his name by showing he had returned his wife’s shareholdings. This event was brought to light when Henry McComb leaked incriminating letters to the Sun newspaper. Schuyler Colfax was axed as a vice presidential nominee as a result of this event, which centered on Oakes Ames’ bribes to Congressmen and other officials. For the point, name this 1867 scandal involving a French-sounding railroad construction company and Ulysses Grant’s administration.", ANSWER: "Credit Mobilier"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "A palace in this city displays the coat of arms of Ludovico Manin in the Scudo Room. A basilica with an octagonal dome was built in this city and dedicated to Saint Mary of Health after a 17th century outbreak of plague; that church stands just east of the Peggy Guggenheim Collection in Dorsoduro. The entrance to a public square in this city is missing a third column, which fell off the boat transporting it more than 800 years ago; the two surviving columns are topped by statues of Saint Theodore and a winged lion. Saint Mark’s Basilica overlooks the largest public square of, for the point, what Italian city famed for its canals?", ANSWER: "Venice"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "Francois Furet and Keith Michael Baker each argue that this man’s writings caused the Terror. This author wrote a novel in which the title character marries Wolmar instead of her tutor Andr ́e Saint-Preux. Another work by this author identifies the human spirit as the source of “perfectibility,” which led to the establishment of society as the origin of inequality. This author of Julie, or the New Helo ̈ıse determined that individuals can be forced to obey the general will in a book that begins “Man is born free, but is everywhere in chains.” For the point, name this author of The Social Contract.", ANSWER: "Rousseau"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This man, who survived a 1919 air crash at Rome-Centocelle airport, used the alias John Hume Ross in an attempt to join the RAF. While in Dera’a, this man was captured by the Ottomans and sexually abused. The future King Faisal I of Iraq led a campaign with this man that included victory at the Battle of Aqaba. This man recounted his experiences in the Arab Revolt in the work Seven Pillars of Wisdom. For the point, name this British soldier of World War I who fought primarily in the Arabian peninsula.", ANSWER: "Lawrence"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "Doctor Robert Huizenga testified that the defendant of this case had the health of “Tarzan’s grandfather.” The defense in this case wanted to show that the central crime was a drug-related Colombian Necktie killing, but Judge Lance Ito barred the related testimony. Robert Kardashian and Johnnie Cochran were among the “Dream Team” of defense lawyers in this case, who stated “If it doesn’t fit, you must acquit” about a glove found near the bodies of Ron Goldman and Nicole Brown. For the point, name this 1995 criminal case in which a former NFL running back was found not guilty of murder.", ANSWER: "Simpson"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "To deal with a product created by this company, John Thach developed a “weave” tactic. James Murphy is one of two known living survivors of labor camps established by this company. In the 1920s, Herbert Smith and other engineers at Sopwith were hired to help make designs for this company. Vehicles nicknamed “Strong Gale” and “Raiden” were created by this company under Jiro Horikoshi. The A6M was designed by, for the point, what aircraft manufacturer whose “Zeroes” were used in World War II kamikaze attacks?", ANSWER: "Mitsubishi"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This man’s brother Richard lifted the Great Siege of Gibraltar and defeated the French Navy during the Glorious First of June. This man scaled the cliffs of Anse-Au-Foulon to provide an avenue for his superior to strike Quebec, and he later executed an amphibious crossing of the Verazzano Narrows to launch a surprise attack at Long Island. Though he won the Battle of Brandywine to capture Philadelphia, his 1778 resignation led to his replacement by Henry Clinton. For the point, name this British general who replaced Thomas Gage after winning the Battle of Bunker Hill.", ANSWER: "Howe"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "The speech that introduced this idea stated that “the culminating and final war for human liberty has come.” Much of this idea was recommended by a group of intellectuals nicknamed The Inquiry, whose research was spearheaded by Walter Lippmann. This idea included the mandate that international relations be conducted in the public view, as well as the outline of the foundation of the League of Nations. Territorial boundaries in Europe were the subject of more than half of, for the point, what numbered set of resolutions laid out by Woodrow Wilson after World War I?", ANSWER: "Fourteen Points"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "Fulwar Skipwith led a breakaway republic from this country’s territory that was annexed by the United States. For 15 years, the U.S. disputed the Neutral Ground with this country, which made secret payments to the first governor of the Louisiana Territory, James Wilkinson. Andrew Jackson led an expedition into this European country’s territory to destroy the Negro Fort. Thomas Pinckney negotiated a 1795 treaty with, for the point, what country that signed the Adams-Onis Treaty with the U.S., in which it ceded claims to Florida?", ANSWER: "Spain"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "The target of this uprising, who had succeeded Samuel Mathews in his highest post, allegedly bared his breast and called for this event’s leader to shoot him. A “Declaration of the People” that was issued as part of this uprising complained that “great unjust taxes upon the commonality” were levied by William Berkeley, who refused to retaliate against surrounding Native American tribes. For the point, name this 1676 rebellion led by a Virginian colonist, the first rebellion in the American colonies.", ANSWER: "Bacon"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "During this war, hospital ships collaborated to treat patients in an area known as “Red Cross Box.” A famous photo of a “Yomper” in this war was taken after commandos navigated “Bomb Alley” to land at San Carlos. One side in this war used Exocet missiles to sink the HMS Sheffield two days after torpedoes sank their cruiser General Belgrano. Within days of the capture of Port Stanley during this war, Leopoldo Galtieri was overthrown and his country began a democratic transition. For the point, name this 1982 war between the U.K. and Argentina over a South Atlantic archipelago.", ANSWER: "Falklands"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "In Germany, this holiday’s “Old Women Day” features women raiding city hall in commemoration of a 1824 washerwoman revolt and involves the eating of the traditional “kreppel” donut. The “Battle of the Oranges” takes place during this holiday in Ivrea, Italy, as people memorialize a struggle against a tyrant. Bandas and Blocos are examples of the samba schools that prominently parade in the world’s largest celebration of this holiday. For the point, name this Christian festive holiday that occurs before Lent and often features public masquerade parties, the largest of which takes place in Rio de Janeiro.", ANSWER: "Carnaval", ANSWER2: "Carnival"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "Note: country and year required. During this election, one politician said that “running through the fields of wheat” was the naughtiest thing she ever did. Paul Nuttall resigned after his party lost over 10 percent of the vote in this election. Despite warning about a “coalition of chaos” of opposing parties, the winner of this election was forced into a confidence and supply agreement with the Democratic Unionist Party. This election saw a surprise surge in seats for the Labour Party under Jeremy Corbyn. For the point, name this snap election in which Conservative Prime Minister Theresa May lost her parliamentary majority.", ANSWER: "2017 UK"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "Charles Maurras led a right-wing organization that formed to counter one side in this event, the Action Fran ̧caise. E ́douard Drumont’s newspaper La Libre Parole was a vocal proponent of one side in this event. This event’s central figure was cleared by an investigation led by Georges Picquart, after which he was freed from Devil’s Island. Clemenceau’s paper L’Aurore and Emile Zola’s open letter “J’accuse” supported the central figure of this affair. Major Ferdinand Esterhazy was the real culprit behind, for the point, what anti-Semitic affair in late 19th century France?", ANSWER: "Dreyfus"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "The first wartime use of Agent Orange occurred in this country during a conflict that was called an “Emergency” rather than a war so that Lloyd’s would cover losses for this country’s two primary industries, tin and rubber. This country fought its southern neighbor during the konfrontasi period, which included a 1962 revolt that ended Brunei’s plans to join this country. In 1970, this country introduced policies to equalize its bumiputera peoples and wealthy Chinese minority. For the point, name this country that absorbed the Bornean states of Sarah, Labuan, and Sarawak in 1963 and whose capital is Kuala Lumpur.", ANSWER: "Malaysia"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "After this man was elected governor, he was sworn into office ten minutes after midnight because he claimed his predecessor had been making too many judicial appointments at the end of his term. This politician joked “it’s just too bad we can’t have an epidemic of botulism” after the Symbionese Liberation Army demanded food be given to the poor after kidnapping Patty Hearst. This politician, who defeated the campaign for a third term for Pat Brown, gave a shining endorsement of Barry Goldwater in his 1964 “A Time for Choosing” speech. For the point, name this Hollywood actor who became Governor of California and, later, US President.", ANSWER: "Reagan"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This character is fatally wounded after he burns papers that were authorized by the King of Spain. Earlier, this character meets the tutor Harriet Winslow while seeking out Pancho Villa’s Army of the North. Those events occur in Carlos Fuentes’ The Old Gringo, a fictionalization of this man’s disappearance during the Mexican Revolution. In a work by this man, a character is distracted by the sound of his watch ticking and imagines his escape from Union soldiers. For the point, name this American author who wrote about Confederate sympathizer Peyton Farquhar in “An Occurrence at Owl Creek Bridge.”", ANSWER: "Bierce"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This event prompted Edward III to pass the Statute of Labourers, which limited wage increases in the face of a declining workforce. Changes in the value of land and labor following this event fatally weakened Western feudalism. This event may have been started by Mongols catapulting dead bodies into the siege of Caffa, and doctors took to wearing bird beaks during it. The Jewish communities of Mainz and Cologne were wiped out on accusations of causing this event, which has been attributed to rat fleas. For the point, name this deadly plague that killed a third of Europe’s population in the 14th century.", ANSWER: "Black Death", ANSWER2: "Black Plague"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "For helping write this law, Ambassador Henry Blair was denied entry into another nation. The Geary Act extended this law, which was meant to last 10 years. In 1943, Franklin Roosevelt supported the Magnuson Act to repeal this legislation. A confession program was created for families who violated this act with the “paper son” ruse. This act, which was meant to target low wage workers derogatorily called “coolies,” led to detentions at Angel Island. For the point, name this 1882 discriminatory act that restricted certain Asians from entering America.", ANSWER: "Chinese Exclusion"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "One of these objects manufactured by Stromberg Carlson appears behind a woman wearing a lampshade in Richard Hamilton’s collage Just what is it that makes today’s homes so different, so appealing?. Nam June Paik’s Electronic Superhighway is an installation that uses many of these devices to show the outline of the United States. Early versions of this technology used cathode ray tubes. Philo Farnsworth improved on the electronic version of, for the point, what technology that was used for The Joy of Painting with Bob Ross on PBS?", ANSWER: "Television", ANSWER2: "TV"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "An inscription saying “Welcome, profit” is written on a floor in this city, where an erotic depiction of Priapus was plastered over. A “secret cabinet” in Naples preserves some scandalous artifacts from this city, whose Garden of Fugitives contains some bodily remains. This city suffered an earthquake seventeen years before an event recorded in letters by Pliny the Younger, whose uncle died in the nearby city of Stabiae. For the point, name this Italian city that was destroyed along with Herculaneum in 79 AD by the eruption of Mount Vesuvius.", ANSWER: "Pompeii"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This man negotiated a cease-fire with General Eulogio Cantillo           to avoid being trapped after the Battle of Las Mercedes. This man’s forces were targeted in Operation Verano in the Sierra Maestra mountains. This man roughly followed Jos ́e Mart ́ı’s journey for a voyage made on a yacht called the Granma. In the July 26th Movement, this man attacked Fulgencio Batista’s forces at the Moncada Barracks. Che Guevara assisted, for the point, what revolutionary who ruled communist Cuba for nearly five decades?", ANSWER: "Castro"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "One ruler with this name saved her husband during the Pruth River Campaign by bribing the Ottomans to permit a retreat. In addition to that ruler, the second wife of Peter the Great, another ruler with this name created the Nakaz legal code and supported Stanislaw Poniatowski’s leadership of the Polish-Lithuanian Commonwealth, which she later partitioned. That monarch patronized Enlightenment figures like Denis Diderot and Voltaire and was advised by former lovers like Grigory Potemkin. For the point, give this name of a female tsar styled “the Great.”", ANSWER: "Catherine"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.3", question: "This man was originally slated to lead the first Gemini mission. This man piloted the Antares, which was the first craft of its kind to use color telecasting equipment. This man, who hit two golf balls on the moon during the Apollo 14 mission, piloted the Freedom Seven on a mission whose primary goal was achieved less than a month prior by the pilot of the Vostok 1, Yuri Gagarin. For the point, name this member of the Mercury Seven, the first American in space.", ANSWER: "Shepard"},
             //2018.NatsBee.4
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "This country’s troops renamed Fort Casimir as Fort Trinity after its capture. This European power exclusively traded firearms to their Native American allies, the Susquehannocks. This country built the first colony along the Delaware River at present-day Wilmington during a voyage in which this country’s people were led by the Dutch captain Peter Minuit. Log cabins were introduced to North America by this country, whose colonial ambitions were effectively ended when Peter Stuyvesant captured Fort Christina. For the point, name this country that colonized what is now Bridgeport, New Jersey as “New Stockholm.”", ANSWER: "Sweden"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "After Germany seized one of this man’s Boeing 737s, he repaid his country’s debt for the Don Mueng Tollway. Ostensibly so that this man could mourn, his reign was preceded by the regency of Prem Tinsulanonda. This man drew ire for throwing a decadent birthday party for his poodle, Fufu, who he later promoted to Air Chief Marshal. Prayut Chan-o-cha serves as Prime Minister under this head of the Chakri Dynasty. For the point, name this man who succeeded his father as King of Thailand in 2016.", ANSWER: "Rama X"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "In his later years, this man bombed Factory-333 and carried out the assassination of Heinz Krug after he was employed by Mossad. This man’s other endeavors included forming the Paladin Group and a group called “the Spider” to help fellow runaways. This man planned the kidnapping of Miklos Horthy’s son in Operation Panzerfaust, as well as Operation Greif, in which his men pretended to be Allied troops during the Battle of the Bulge. For the point, name this German paratroop commander who rescued Benito Mussolini in the Gran Sasso raid.", ANSWER: "Skorzeny"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "This speech refutes a comparison between its central theme and a rebel who holds out against a prince, likening that theme instead to a person stomping on a worm. This speech, which begins with the quote “Their Foot shall slide in due Time,” compares its central subjects to a spider dangled over an open flame. This speech, which was first delivered in Northampton and Enfield, argues that it is only through God’s grace that the wicked are given a chance to avoid hell. For the point, name this fiery sermon delivered by Jonathan Edwards during the First Great Awakening.", ANSWER: "Sinners in the Hands of an Angry God"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Description acceptable. According to one legend, the first holder of this position was given a golden staff to mark the place where a temple was to be created. Titu Cusi held this position before a successor who was attacked by Francisco de Toledo in the Vilcabamba Valley; that holder of this position inspired the name of a 1781 rebellion against a Viceroyalty. The first holder of this position was Manco Capac. Tupac Amaru was the last holder of, for the point, what position, the ruler of a major Peruvian empire?", ANSWER: "Emperor of the Inca", ANSWER2: "King of the Inca", ANSWER3: "Sapa"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Benjamin Thorpe edited six sections of this work for the Rolls Series. A subsection of this text was destroyed in a fire at a church in Peterborough. An unusually lengthy section of this work describes Sigeberht’s death at the hands of Cynewulf. This work introduced bretwalda, a kingly title held by Raedwald of East Anglia and seven others, and was partially translated by the bishop Asser. For the point, name this text, composed under Alfred the Great in the 9th century, that chronicles the history of the group that dominated England prior to the Norman Conquest.", ANSWER: "Anglo-Saxon Chronicle"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Benjamin, a politician with this surname, managed the New York Daily News for forty years in the late 1800s. When George Walling attempted to arrest a politician with this surname, he called in the Municipal police force, causing a police riot; that politician, Fernando, was a two-time Democratic mayor of New York City. Theodore Roosevelt was second in command to a military officer of this surname in a cavalry corps active in the Spanish-American War. For the point, give this surname of Leonard, the leader of the Rough Riders.", ANSWER: "Wood"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Evidence of this event was found in the DNA of teeth found in a mass grave at the Keramaikos Cemetery. A ship from Africa entering the Piraeus may have instigated this event, which Thucydides refused to blame on the gods. Many who believed that Apollo chose a side in the Peloponnesian War did so because of this event, which caused bad breath, spasms, ulcers, bleeding, and fever. Typhoid has been deduced as the cause of, for the point, what tragic event in summer 430 BC that killed Pericles and one-third of a major Greek city?", ANSWER: "Athens plague"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Charles Fabry and Alfred Perot developed an instrument crucial to the operation of this project, which had to achieve seismic isolation. Ronald Drever was a co-founder of this project, but passed away seven months before a Nobel Prize was awarded for it. Proposed following the work of Rainer Weiss and Kip Thorne, this project was the largest NSF-funded endeavor of all time. Caltech and MIT jointly operate this project, which has detectors in Washington and Louisiana that have observed black hole collisions. For the point, name this project that finally detected gravitational waves in 2015.", ANSWER: "LIGO"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "This man pointed out that vertical integration and price discrimination were punished despite not harming consumers in his book The Antitrust Paradox. Ted Kennedy claimed that, in this man’s America,” women would be forced into back-alley abortions and blacks would sit at segregated lunch counters.” As Solicitor General, this man ultimately carried out Nixon’s order to fire special prosecutor Archibald Cox. Anthony Kennedy received his highest post after only 42 Senators voted to confirm, for the point, what man whose 1987 nomination to the Supreme Court was rejected?", ANSWER: "Bork"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "An intelligence mission prior to this battle was codenamed Trudy Jackson. Forrest Sherman supported a plan for this battle after hearing the story of an escape from Corregidor. Wolmido island was bombarded heavily before this battle, which included the capture of Kimpo Airfield and landings at Red, Green and Blue beaches. The Second Battle of Seoul followed this battle, which was created as a diversion for UN troops defending the Pusan Perimeter. For the point, name this 1950 Korean War amphibious invasion, the brainchild of Douglas MacArthur.", ANSWER: "Inchon"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "In this year, Eli Hart’s store was attacked by a mob in the Flour Riot. A stunning Whig electoral victory in this year’s state-level elections was dubbed a “New York tornado” by the sitting president. In this year, Congress began talks about a Divorce Bill to create an independent treasury system. The president who was inaugurated in this year received the nickname “ruin,” as hundreds of banks failed in the second nationwide economic panic in American history. For the point, name this year of Martin van Buren’s inauguration.", ANSWER: "1837"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "A novel by this author includes the Witchcraft scheme, whereby one man trades valuable information, or gold dust, for worthless information, or chicken feed. In a novel by this author, Liz Gold is shot and killed while crossing an international border and The Circus uses Alec Leamas as their unwitting pawn to protect a former Nazi. A nursery rhyme about a “rich man, poor man, / beggarman, thief” provides the title of a novel by this author in which Control tasks George Smiley with finding a mole. For the point, name this member of Britain’s MI6 and author of the Cold War-era novels The Spy Who Came in from the Cold and Tinker Tailor Soldier Spy.", ANSWER: "le Carre"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "A village near this city had its iron doors shipped to London by Sir Reginald Stubbs. Possession Street marks Edward Belcher’s landing in this city, and Boundary Street used to form a border for this city. The Third Plague ravaged this city, possibly because of the Peak Reservation Ordinance that segregated this city’s Victoria Peak. Norman Foster built the headquarters for a bank named for this city and Shanghai. Following the First Opium War, this city became a British colony under the Treaty of Nanjing. For the point, name this southern Chinese city that was returned to China in 1997.", ANSWER: "Hong Kong"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "An event named after this type of location was investigated by the fraudulent Burdenko Commission and by the writer Ferdynand Goetel. A battle named after this type of location culminated in a massacre near Kalkriese Hill, where heavy rains bogged down three legions under the command of Publius Varus. The NKVD executed thousands of Polish officers and buried them in one of these locations named Katyn.GermanictribesmenunderthecommandofArminiuswonabattlenamedafterthe Teutoberg type of this location. Fortifications in the spa town of Baden-Baden are found in, for the point, the Black example of what type of wooded area?", ANSWER: "Forest"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Antonia Novello was the first woman to hold this position, in which capacity she criticized advertising mascots like Old Joe. Joycelyn Elders was a controversial holder of this position under Bill Clinton who proposed the legalization of drugs to stop crime. Holders of this position included C. Everett Koop, who authored a report on the psychological effects of abortion, and Luther Terry, who released a 1964 study that linked cigarette smoking to various diseases. For the point, name this position in the federal government held by a public health expert.", ANSWER: "Surgeon General"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "This leader described the invasion of Czechoslovakia as a “serious danger to peace in Europe” in the 21st of August speech. This leader, who overhauled his security forces after the defection of Ion Pacepa, called for a “mini cultural revolution” in his July Theses and heavily restricted access to contraceptives as part of his Decree 770. The eviction order of pastor Laszlo Tokes       led to protests against this leaderinTimisoara.Thisleaderwasoverthrownandexecutedbyafiringsquadwithhis wife Elena on Christmas Day 1989. For the point, name this former Communist dictator of Romania.", ANSWER: "Ceausescu"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "A type of ensemble from this country, featuring the oboe-like zurna and the davul, was known as the mehteran. Mozart’s Violin Concerto no. 5 was nicknamed for this country, and specially-manufactured pianos often played his Piano Sonata no. 11, which ends with a rondo named for this country. Triangles, bass drums, and cymbals were imported into Western orchestras from this country following its wars with the Hapsburg Empire. For the point, a Classical-era craze for the music of what country was inspired by the Janissary military bands of the Ottoman Empire?", ANSWER: "Turkey"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Many commencement speakers have used this figure’s quote “The greatest crime in the world is not developing your potential.” A book by this figure introduced the words “moccasin” and “moose” to the English language. This figure argued that the Parable of the Tares supported tolerance of religious “weeds” in a dialogue between Truth and Peace, The Bloudy Tenent of Persecution. This man allied with the Narragansett after he was expelled from Massachusetts for heresy. Providence was founded by, for the point, what creator of the colony of Rhode Island?", ANSWER: "Williams"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "During this event, the so-called “first relief force” of Henry Havelock was so small that it, too, became besieged until the arrival of Colin Campbell. The troops of the Nana Sahib massacred civilians attempting to escape Cawnpore during this event. This event, which led to the exile of Bahadur Shah II, was sparked by the rumored use of animal fat in cartridge grease that offended both Hindus and Muslims. For the point, name this revolution against the British East India Company in India.", ANSWER: "Sepoy"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "This leader’s foreign minister, Abba Eban, once quipped that this person spoke using only 200 words out of a vocabulary of 500. This person’s home country gave out its first passport to send this person to Moscow as minister to Russia in 1948. This leader lost power after being cleared by the Agranat Commission, though this leader’s reputation was still tarnished by the weak response to a troop buildup on the Golan Heights. For the point, name this Israeli prime minister during the Yom Kippur War, the only woman to have held the post.", ANSWER: "Golda Meir"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "German colonists in this state’s Fisher-Miller Land Grant organized posses that triggered the Hoodoo War. A dispute over public ownership of lakes triggered the Salt War in this state’s town of San Elizario. A five year long feud in this state in the 19th century was fought between the Regulators and the Moderators. This state and its western neighbor were the origin of the Fence Cutting Wars over grazing rights of cattlemen and land owners. For the point, name this state where Range Wars were suppressed by a police force of its namesake Rangers.", ANSWER: "Texas"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "During this event, Mary Putland and her father were imprisoned in Government House. A man deposed in this incident had previously dismissed Thomas Jamison for being “inimical” to good government. Prior to this event, John McArthur was told to appear in court. George Johnston led troops to arrest a leader during this event, which was finally ended when Lachlan Macquarie was made governor. William Bligh was deposed as governor of New South Wales in, for the point, what 1808 Australian rebellion that was initially blamed on a namesake alcoholic beverage?", ANSWER: "Rum"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Robert Park’s “Urban Ecology” theory was developed at this university, whose concentric circle model for city development was created by Ernest Burgess. A Henry Moore sculpture commemorates the former location of this school’s Stagg Field. This school’s sociology department worked with local city activists such as Ellen Gates Starr and Jane Addams. A prominent school of economics is based in, for the point, what university initially funded by John D. Rockefeller, located in Hyde Park on the South Side of a major Midwestern city?", ANSWER: "Chicago", ANSWER2: "UChicago"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "This man originally went into the banking business with Gianetto Berardi, who helped finance ChristopherColumbus’voyages.UnderGon ̧caloCoelho-lo,thismanwaspartofa 1501-1502 voyage that allegedly reached Patagonia. This explorer is thought to have been the first to sight the mouths of both the Orinoco and Amazon rivers. This native of Florence disproved previous theories that the West Indies were a part of Asia. The creator of the Universalis Cosmographia map used the name of, for the point, what explorer whose name inspired that of two New World continents?", ANSWER: "Vespucci"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "An incident in the Seventy-Niner’s Caf ́e in this city’s African-American neighborhood of Hough sparked a 1966 riot. Zoning ordinances were legitimized in the US by a Supreme Court case involving this city’s suburb of Euclid. This city’s four-block Public Square is overlooked by Key Tower and was designed by its namesake, a shareholder from the Connecticut Land Company. This city is also home to the mouth of a river that “caught fire” in 1969. The Cuyahoga River flows into Lake Erie in, for the point, what city, home to Case Western Reserve University in northeastern Ohio?", ANSWER: "Cleveland"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: " leader was able to turn the tide of this battle after the sudden arrival from Amurru of one side’s Caananite mercenaries. Prior to this battle, one side sent two Shasu nomads to mislead the other advancing side about its whereabouts and recruited nineteen allies, including the king of Aleppo. In this battle, the Ra and Amun divisions were initially routed by attacks across the Orontes River launched by Muwatalli II. Ramses II clashed with the Hittite Empire at, for the point, what ancient battle, said to be the largest chariot battle in recorded history?", ANSWER: "Kadesh"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "After the McClellan Committee investigated this man, George Meany essentially ordered this man’s removal from power. This man’s son contested Ron Carey’s electoral defeat shortly after Carey had led that man’s union in a 1997 UPS strike. This man negotiated the National Master Freight Agreement that extended protections to over 450,000 drivers. After meeting two Mafia men at the Red Fox Restaurant in 1975, this man mysteriously disappeared. For the point, name this leader of the Teamsters.", ANSWER: "Hoffa"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "A series of fortifications at this battle were named for London, Rouen and Paris. Prior to this battle, Robert de Baudricourt met with this engagement’s most famous participant three times. Jean of Dunois led a defense in this battle against William de la Pole. Following this battle, a series of battles, including one at Patay, were fought in the Loire Campaign. During this battle, John Talbot ended his attack after Fort St. Loup fell. The Battle of the Herrings proceeded, for the point, what 1428-29 siege that was broken by the arrival of Joan of Arc?", ANSWER: "Orleans"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Conservative fears that policy was being embraced too closely inspired the “Team B” study. Enthusiastic American responses to this policy included the Jackson-Vanik amendment, which permitted trade relations in exchange for the allowance of Jewish emigration. This policy, which was less aggressive than rollback and containment, culminated in the signing of treaties like the Helsinki Accords and SALT I. For the point, give this French term for Richard Nixon’s easing of tensions with the Soviet Union.", ANSWER: "Detente"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Performing this action was the goal of the “Crimson” aspect of the hypothetical War Plan Red. A loss at the Battle of Queenston Heights blocked one attempt to accomplish this feat. The death of Richard Montgomery and a naval defeat at the Battle of Valcour Island decisively ended Benedict Arnold’s attempts to do this. James Wolfe was mortally wounded at the Battle of the Plains of Abraham during a British instance of, for the point, what military action that the US unsuccessfully tried to perform in the 1775 attack on Quebec?", ANSWER: "Invading Canada", ANSWER2: "Invasion of Canada", ANSWER3: "invading Ontario", ANSWER4: "invading Quebec"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Edouard Manet painted a full-length portrait of Mademoiselle Victorine, an assistant to one of these people called an espada; in that portrait, the subject holds a pink scarf, rather than the more accurate red. A print series about this profession includes works showing the death of an impaled picador and Juan Apin ̃ani pole-vaulting over a charging animal. Francisco Goya’s print series Tauromaquia depicts, for the point, what athletes who compete after the “running” of their animal opponents to the arena in Pamplona?", ANSWER: "Bullfighter", ANSWER2: "Matador", ANSWER3: "Toreador"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "Two answers required. After a scientific breakthrough in one of these two countries, the leader of the other gave a speech stating that “The East Wind Prevails Over the West.” One of these two countries allied with Albania in defiance of the other after denouncing the other as “revisionist” because of the “Secret Speech.” One of these two countries withdrew its advisors to the other after its policy of “peaceful coexistance” was criticized during the Great Leap Forward. For the point, name these two countries that “split” in the 1960s, despite being the largest Communist countries in the world.", ANSWER: "China Soviet Union", ANSWER2: "China USSR"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "This nation saw the rise of the ultra-nationalist Mkhedrioni, or “Horsemen,” which launched asuccessfulcoupagainstitsfirstpresident,ZviadGamsakhurdia. This nation, which heavily shelled the city of Sukhumi in a 1992-1993 war, had its longtime president Eduard Shevardnadze peacefully deposed by protesters and replaced by Mikhail Saakashvili in the Rose Revolution. For the point, name this country that does not recognize the Republic of South Ossetia, which broke away from this country with Russian assistance.", ANSWER: "Georgia"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "This city was the subject of a 2014 Ben Reiter prediction that proved true despite a mishap involving Mark Appel. This city’s baseball team signed the first million-dollars-per-year MLB contract and built the world’s first domed stadium. Another sport created a lottery system after a team from this city “tanked” to win the first pick in the 1984 draft; that team’s current General Manager, Daryl Morey, names an offense that relies on three pointers and layups and was led by James Harden to the Western Conference’s best record in 2018. For the point, name this city, home to basketball’s Rockets and baseball’s defending champion Astros.", ANSWER: "Houston"},
             {date: "2018.NatsBee.4", question: "A Christian Democratic President of this country launched reforms like “social promotion,” agrarian reform, and education reform; later, that President backed the electoral opponent of Jorge Alessandri. Marcelo Moren Brito operated a torture facility at the Villa Grimaldi in this country. The apolitical nature of this country’s military was briefly upheld by the Schneider Doctrine. One leader of this country operated a “Caravan of Death,” which used helicopters to execute political opponents. For the point, name this country that has been led by Salvador Allende and Augusto Pinochet.", ANSWER: "Chile"},
            ];
